Finding Aid for Center for Middle Eastern and North African Studies (University of Michigan) records 1949-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Center for Middle Eastern and North African Studies (University of Michigan) records
1949-1997
1960-1997
University of Michigan. Center for Middle Eastern and North African Studies.
Interdisciplinary area studies center at the University of Michigan. Records include material from the Department of Near Eastern Studies predating the founding of the center as well as files on center directors, conferences, seminars, and lectures. Administrative files include executive committee minutes beginning in 1971, center reviews and evaluations, and records on funding and funding agencies.
9821 Bimu 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
8 linear feet
The records were transferred by the Center for Middle Eastern and North African Studies (donor # 8554 ) in 1997.
The records are open for research.
The Center for Middle Eastern and North African Studies (CMENAS) was created by the University of Michigan in 1961. It was originally called the Center for Near and Middle Eastern Studies, which was changed to the Center for Near Eastern and North African Studies in 1963, and was changed once again in 1991 to its current name. The Center was one of many "area centers" established at American universities in the post-World War II era. Following the war, American foreign policy makers argued that a lack of American expertise in foreign language and culture had hindered the U.S. war effort, and that this deficiency would continue to weaken the nation's global position. Area centers were intended to remedy this weakness by encouraging intense interdisciplinary scholarship with a strong focus on the mastery of language. In 1947, the University of Michigan established its first area studies center, the Center for Japanese Studies.
The Center for Middle Eastern and North African Studies was the product of an expansion of area studies at the university proposed by the College of Literature, Science and the Arts (LS&A) in 1959. LS&A appointed a committee chaired by anthropology professor William Schorger to develop the proposal. The committee recommended the creation of four new centers: the Center for Chinese Studies, the Center for Russian and Eastern European Studies, the Center for South and Southeast Asian Studies, and the Center for Near and Middle Eastern Studies. In 1961, the university secured a large grant from the Ford Foundation to carry out the proposal, and launched the new centers. Schorger was appointed director of the Center for Near and Middle Eastern Studies.
The new center drew upon the faculty of a variety of academic departments. Professors from the extant Department of Near Eastern Studies, who were mostly language experts, provided the core of the center's faculty; they were joined by faculty from history, anthropology, economics, the history of art, and other disciplines whose work concerned the Middle East or North Africa.
The center's main objectives are to coordinate research on the Middle East and North Africa and to train experts on those regions. In its first decade, the center primarily fulfilled these goals by funding faculty instruction and research, providing fellowships to students, and supporting library acquisitions. In the 1970s and 1980s, the center expanded its activities by hosting academic conferences, sponsoring lectures, and developing workshops on the Middle East for secondary school instructors. In the 1990s, the Center has continued its varied activities, supported by federal grants under the Title VI National Resource Center and Foreign Language Fellowships Program.
The records of the Center for Middle Eastern and North African Studies document the founding and functioning of the center, from the 1960s to the 1990s, and include historical materials about the Department of Near Eastern Studies dating from the 1940s and 1950s. The records cover the center's history fairly evenly, but document the period from the 1970s to the 1990s in greater depth than the center's first decade. While the 1960s are documented in correspondence, funding reports, and press clippings, records from the later decade also include executive committee minutes, material from conferences and lectures, and photographs. The CMENAS records cover a variety of topics related to the history, politics, economy, literature and art of the Middle East. Furthermore, the records document how American universities studied those topics from the 1940s to the 1990s.
The records are arranged in twelve series: Area Centers Material, Executive Committee, Evaluation, Funding, Historical Material, Intra-University Programs, Name File, National Organizations, Outreach, Publications Related Files, Special Activities, and Photographs.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Center for Middle Eastern and North African Studies.; Middle East--Study and teaching.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Near Eastern Studies.; Persian Gulf War, 1991--Study and teaching.
Subjects - Visual Material:
University of Michigan. Center for Middle Eastern and North African Studies.; Middle East--Study and teaching.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Near Eastern Studies.; Mitchell, Richard P. (Richard Paul), 1925-; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.
Contributors:
Mitchell, Richard P. (Richard Paul), 1925-; McCarus, Ernest N. (Ernest Nasseph), 1922-; Cole, Juan Ricardo.; Grabar, Oleg.; Grassmuck, George.; Abdel-Massih, Ernest T.; Cameron, George G. (George Glenn), 1905-1979; Hourani, George Fadlo.; Schorger, William D.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Area Centers Material
  The Area Centers Material consists of correspondence, memos, and reports related to the university's various area centers from the 1960s through the 1990s. It includes material related to the establishment of the Institute for Foreign Area and International Studies, a university office charged with overseeing the operations of the area centers.
  - Area Centers Committee
    - 1962-1964 (Box 1)
    - 1964-1980 (Box 1)
  - Area Centers Review Committee, 1991 (Box 1)
  - LS&A Review of Area Centers
    - 1981 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Institute for Foreign Area and International Studies (IFAIS)
    - Area Studies Reorganization; "Supercenter" Proposal, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Director Search, 1993 (Box 1)
    - David Cohen; Electronic Mail, 1993 (Box 1)
- Executive Committee
  The Executive Committee series consists of two subseries. The larger of these subseries is made up of executive committee minutes from the 1970s through the 1990s. The minutes cover a wide variety of topics including funding, budgeting outreach activities, appointments, and admissions. The second subseries concerns elections to the executive committee.
  - Minutes
    - 1971-1975 (Box 1)
    - 1975-1977 (Box 1)
    - 1977-1980 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1982 (Box 1)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 1)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - 1985-1986, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 1)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - 1988 (Box 1)
    - 1989 (Box 1)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 1)
    - 1991 (Box 1)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - 1992 (Box 1)
    - 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    - 1993 (Box 1)
  - Elections
    - 1972-1990 (Box 1)
- Evaluation
  The Evaluation series consists of reports and correspondence concerning evaluations of the center from the 1970s through the 1990s. The series documents both internal reviews conducted by the center, and external evaluations of the CMENAS budget and activities by the university.
  - Program Evaluation, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - Evaluation and Planning Project, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Program Evaluation, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Review of Center, 1982-1983 (Box 1)
  - Internal Review, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Internal Review, 1983; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Center Report, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Student Survey, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Center Review, to Area Centers Review Committee, 1991 (Box 2)
  - External Review
    - 1989-191991 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1991 (Box 2)
    - 1992 (Box 2)
    - Center Response, 1992; 3 folders (Box 2)
- Funding
  The Funding subseries consists of correspondence, reports, and memos related to the funding of the center from the 1960s through the 1990s. It is divided into two subseries: internal funding and external funding. The internal funding subseries includes material on the center budget and grants awarded by the center to faculty and students. The external funding subseries concerns grants awarded to the center by private foundations, corporations, and government agencies, and is arranged alphabetically by the name of the granting agency. The subseries also contains correspondence and writings by Middle-Eastern intellectuals who were rewarded Rockefeller fellowships to teach or research at the University of Michigan.
  - Internal Funding
    - Center Budget, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    - CMENAS Faculty Enrichment Fellowship, 1984-1991 (Box 2)
  - External Funding
    - Ad-hoc Committee on Middle East Funding, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Carnegie Foundation, 1989 (Box 2)
    - U.S. Department of Education
      - Grant Reports
        - 1980-1981 (Box 2)
        - 1982-1983 (Box 2)
        - 1983-1984 (Box 2)
        - 1984-1985 (Box 2)
    - U.S. Department of Education (Box 3)
      - Grant Reports
        - 1986-1987 (Box 3)
      - Higher Education Act Title VI Applications
        - 1982-1983 (Box 3)
        - 1984-1985 (Box 3)
        - 1987-1988 (Box 3)
        - 1988-1989 (Box 3)
        - 1989-1990 (Box 3)
        - 1990-1991 (Box 3)
      - International Research and Studies Program Grant: Juan Cole, "Evaluating Textbooks", 1994-1995 (Box 3)
    - Exxon Corporation, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Ford Foundation
      - Summary Report of Activities to Foundation, 1961-1966 (Box 3)
      - Cooperative International Studies, Report to Foundation, 1965 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Fullbright Foundation
      - Grant for Syria Trip, 1994 (Box 3)
      - Research Application for Hamdi Qafisheh, 1991 (Box 3)
    - MacArthur Foundation, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Mellon Foundation; Correspondence and Reports
      - 1989, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1989-1990 (Box 3)
      - 1989-1992 (Box 3)
      - 1990-1994 (Box 3)
      - 1991 (Box 3)
    - Middle East Institute
      - Study Tour for Secondary Teachers, 1991 (Box 3)
      - Study Tour in the Levant, 1992-1994 (Box 3)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities Grant: Ronald Stockton, "The Arab World and the West", 1994-1995 (Box 3)
    - Presidential Initiatives Fund, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Rockefeller Foundation
      - Application, 1989 (Box 3)
      - Committee, 1986 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence
        - 1987-1992 (Box 3)
        - 1988-1992 (Box 3)
      - Evaluation, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Rockefeller Foundation (Box 4)
      - Fellows: Correspondence and Writings
        - Mashid Amir-Shahy, 1990-1991 (Box 4)
        - Sarah Atis, 1990-1991 (Box 4)
        - Samar Attar, 1990-1991 (Box 4)
        - Mohammed Gahoonpavar, 1989-1993 (Box 4)
        - Salman Jayyusi, 1986-1990 (Box 4)
        - Ali Salem
          - 1989-1991 (Box 4)
          - 1990-1991 (Box 4)
        - Anton Shammas
          - 1988-1991 (Box 4)
          - 1990-1994 (Box 4)
        - Bassam Tibi
          - 1988-1990 (Box 4)
          - 1990-1992 (Box 4)
      - Grant Proposals
        - 1985-1989 (Box 4)
        - 1986 (Box 4)
        - 1986-1987 (Box 4)
        - 1989-1990 (Box 4)
      - Publicity, 1985-1986 (Box 4)
      - Report
        - 1988 (Box 4)
        - 1989-1990 (Box 4)
        - 1990-1991 (Box 4)
    - Social Science Research Council, 1989 (Box 4)
- Historical Material
  The Historical Material series consists of a variety of material relating to the history of both CMENAS and the Department of Near Eastern Studies. The material from the Department for Near Eastern Studies dates from the late 1940s to the early 1960s. The CMENAS material dates from the 1960s through the 1990s, and includes histories and descriptions of the center, newspaper clippings relating to the center and its faculty, Center directories, and material relating to the center's move from Lane Hall.
  - Clippings
    - Regarding Center
      - 1960-1985 (Box 4)
      - 1986-1992 (Box 4)
    - Near Eastern Professors in the News, 1982 (Box 4)
  - Center Directories, 1970-1989 (Box 4)
  - Committee on Near Eastern Studies, "A Program for Near Eastern Studies in the United States", 1949 (Box 4)
  - Department of Near Eastern Studies
    - Correspondence and Memos
      - 1949-1957 (Box 4)
      - 1957-1962 (Box 4)
    - Near East Expedition, 1951 (Box 4)
    - Summer Institute
      - 1950 (Box 4)
      - 1952 (Box 4)
  - General Historical and Descriptive Material
    - 1961-1972 (Box 4)
    - 1965-1990 (Box 4)
  - Lane Hall; Material Regarding Space, 1984-1989 (Box 4)
  - Material for LS&A History, 1979-1980 (Box 4)
- Intra-University Programs
  The Intra-University Programs series is made up of correspondence and reports relating to two joint-degree programs: the joint law/Near Eastern studies masters program, and the joint business administration/Near Eastern studies masters program. These records date from the 1970s through the 1990s.
  - Joint Law/ Near Eastern Studies Program
    - 1977-1978 (Box 4)
    - 1985-1986 (Box 4)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 4)
    - 1995 (Box 4)
    - 1995-1996 (Box 4)
  - Joint MBA/ Near Eastern Studies Program
    - 1982-1983 (Box 4)
    - 1984 (Box 4)
    - 1986-1989 (Box 5)
    - 1992-1993 (Box 5)
- Name File
  The Name File series consists of correspondence, curriculum vitae and writings by or about center faculty, dating from the 1960s through the 1990s. The series is organized alphabetically by the name of the professor. The series includes the official correspondence of two directors of CMENAS, Juan Cole and William Schorger, and one folder of staff memos from the early 1960s.
  - Ernest Abdel-Massih
    - General Material, 1968-1980 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 5)
    - Memorials, 1982 (Box 5)
  - George Cameron, 1969-1974 (Box 5)
  - Juan Cole; Director's Correspondence
    - 1993-1995, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Douglas Crary
    - 1964-1971, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Andrew Ehrenkreutz, 1964-1990 (Box 5)
  - David Freedman, 1985-1992 (Box 5)
  - Oleg Grabbar
    - 1965-1990, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - George Grassmuck
    - Biographical and bibliographical
      - 1967-1991 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence
      - 1963-1967 (Box 5)
      - 1965-1991 (Box 5)
  - George Hourani, 1966-1967 (Box 5)
  - John Kolars
    - 1962-1966 (Box 5)
    - 1969-1992 (Box 5)
    - Courses and Conferences, 1990-1992 (Box 5)
    - General, 1990-1991 (Box 5)
  - Kenneth A. Luther
    - General, 1966-1971 (Box 5)
    - Memorials and General Material, 1966-1997 (Box 5)
    - Retirement, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Ernest McCarus; General, 1966-1992 (Box 5)
  - George Mendenhall
    - Clippings, 1996 (Box 5)
    - General, 1964-1984 (Box 5)
  - Richard Mitchell
    - Correspondence
      - 1963-1966 (Box 5)
      - 1966-1981 (Box 5)
    - General, 1965-1981 (Box 5)
  - Louis Orlin, 1964-1981 (Box 5)
  - Herbert Paper, 1964-1988 (Box 5)
  - William Schorger
    - 1966-1969 (Box 5)
    - 1966-1983 (Box 5)
    - 1967-1969 (Box 5)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 5)
    - 1967-1971 (Box 5)
    - 1982-1986 (Box 5)
    - 1986 (Box 6)
  - John Waterbury
    - 1967 (Box 6)
    - 1967-1970 (Box 6)
  - Staff Memos, 1961-1965 (Box 6)
- National Organizations
  The National Organizations series is made up of correspondence with professional and intellectual organizations and research consortiums from the 1980s and 1990s.
  - American Oriental Society-Society for Biblical Literature; Meeting, 1981 (Box 6)
  - Asia Institute, correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 6)
  - Center for Iranian Research and Analysis; 9th Annual Conference, 1991 (Box 6)
  - Middle East Studies Association/ Middle East Outreach Council; Text Evaluation Project 1991 Program for Inter-Institutional Cooperation in Area Studies, 1987-1988 (Box 6)
  - Social Science Research Council; Programs, 1994-1995 (Box 6)
  - Turkish/ Persian Consortium
    - 1988-1994 (Box 6)
    - 1993 (Box 6)
- Outreach
  The Outreach series documents a variety of outreach activities, including language workshops and roundtables, the development of secondary school curriculum, workshops for secondary schoolteachers, and travel programs. These activities share the common goal of reaching out beyond the small community of professional scholars and policy experts to educate a broader audience about the Middle East and North Africa. The outreach records date from the 1980s and 1990s.
  - Arab Proficiency Workshop, 1994 (Box 6)
  - Curriculum Development for Secondary Schools, 1975-1979 (Box 6)
  - Language Roundtables, 1982-1988 (Box 6)
  - Media Briefings
    - 1982-1985 (Box 6)
    - 1986-1993 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Outreach Material
    - 1982-1988 (Box 6)
    - 1982-1985 (Box 6)
    - 1986-1993 (Box 6)
    - 1992-1994 (Box 6)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 6)
  - Seminars, 1986-1987 (Box 6)
  - Summer Institute for College Teachers, 1984 (Box 6)
  - Summer Seminars for Secondary Teachers
    - 1986 (Box 6)
    - 1987 (Box 6)
    - 1988 (Box 6)
    - 1988-1993 (Box 6)
  - Teacher's Workshops
    - Saturday Workshop, 1987 (Box 6)
    - "Water and Oil," Workshop, 1988 (Box 6)
  - Travel, 1991-1993 (Box 6)
- Publications Related Files
  The Publications series consists of correspondence and memos about the center's publication activities in the 1980s and 1990s.
  - Correspondence
    - 1987-1992 (Box 6)
    - 1989-1991 (Box 6)
  - General, 1986-1989 (Box 6)
- Special Activities
  The Special Activities subseries consists of correspondence, papers, and publicity from conferences and lectures sponsored by CMENAS in the 1980s and 1990s. The series is divided into a two subseries: conferences and lectures. Both of these subseries are organized chronologically.
  - Conferences: chronological
    - Roundtable on Iran and Afghanistan, 1980 (Box 6)
    - U.S. Policy Towards the Middle East-Symposium, 1982; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Conference on the Middle East: Arab Student Organization, 1983 (Box 6)
    - "The Roles of Women in the Changing Middle East", 1983
      - General (Box 6)
      - Papers (Box 6)
    - "Current Trends in Foreign Policy Under the Reagan Administration", 1984 (Box 6)
    - "Development Policies and their Consequences", 1984 (Box 6)
    - "The United States and the Search for Peace in the Middle East", 1984 (Box 6)
    - Conference on Literature and Politics, 1985 (Box 6)
    - "The Soviet Union and its Muslim Neighbors", 1985 (Box 6)
    - International Economic Development Symposium, 1986 (Box 6)
    - Symposium on Yemen and Labor Migration to Detroit, 1986 (Box 6)
    - "The Age of Suleyman the Magnificent", 1987 (Box 7)
    - Arab American Conference, 1988-1989; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - "Literature in the Contemporary Middle East", 1988 (Box 7)
    - "The Winds of Change", 1988 (Box 7)
    - "An Agenda for the 1990s", 1989 (Box 7)
    - "A Global Agenda for the Bush Administration," Symposium, 1989 (Box 7)
    - "Armenian Odyssey II," Symposium, 1990 (Box 7)
    - "The Jews of Islamic Lands", 1990 (Box 7)
    - Middle East Computer Conferences, 1990 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous Conference Material, 1991-1993 (Box 7)
    - Arab American Conference, 1990 (Box 7)
    - Religious Revival Symposium, 1991 (Box 7)
    - Symposium on Arab Linguistics 1991 "Close Encounters of the Cultural Kind", 1991 (Box 7)
    - "Gender and Society in the Middle East" 1991 Teach-in On the Gulf Crisis, 1991 (Box 7)
    - Conference on Gulf War, 1991 (Box 7)
    - "The Role of the Intellectual in the Nineteenth and Twentieth Century Mediterranean Basin", 1992-1993 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous Conference Material, 1992-1995 (Box 7)
    - "1492 Perspectives from North Africa and the Middle East", 1992 (Box 7)
    - Gender Issues in the Middle East, 1994 (Box 7)
  - Lectures: chronological
    - Miscellaneous Lecture Material
      - 1981-1982 (Box 7)
      - 1983-1985, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - "Focus on Women," Lecture Series, 1984-1985; 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous Lecture Material
      - 1986 (Box 7)
      - 1986-1987 (Box 7)
    - Center's 25th Anniversary Lectures, 1986-1987; 9 folders (Box 7)
    - Middle East Faculty Seminar, 1987-1988 (Box 8)
    - Martin Luther King Day Presentations, 1989-1997 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous Lectures, 1992 (Box 8)
    - Brown Bag Lecture Series, 1993 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous Lectures, 1993-1994 (Box 8)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series consists of photographs from the center. Most of the photographs picture CMENAS staff, faculty and students at CMENAS social events. The series also includes several undated photographs of CMENAS classes and offices, and one photograph of visiting professor Mashid Amirshay. The photographs date from the late-1980s and the 1990s.
  - Mitchell Prize, 1987 (Box 8)
  - End of the Academic Year Celebration 1988 Iranian New Year, 1989 Semester End Celebration, 1990 (Box 8)
  - Winter Celebration, 1990 (Box 8)
  - End of the Year Celebration, 1991 (Box 8)
  - Open House, 1992 (Box 8)
  - End of the Term Celebration, 1992 (Box 8)
  - End of the Year Celebration; Mitchell Prize, 1993 (Box 8)
  - Mitchell Prize and Semester End Celebration, 1994 (Box 8)
  - Open House and Winter Break Party, 1994 (Box 8)
  - End of the Year Celebration and Graduation Reception, 1995 (Box 8)
  - Photographs of Center Activities, undated (Box 8)
  - Mashid Amirshahy; Visiting Professor, 1990-1991 (Box 8)